hello everyone and welcome back to
active inference insights I'm your host
darus parv Wayne and today I'm delighted
to be speaking to Vana Visa van is a
postdoctoral fellow at Johannes
Gutenberg University mines in the
department of Ro University B sorry the
internet has lied to me the internet has
lied to me I don't like this
introduction bit already um but I think
this is true nonetheless his research
centers on Consciousness medal rep
presentation philosophy of cognitive
science philosophy of mind and of course
Act of inference uh we also both share a
love of self- modeling attention
autopoetic intentionality and much much
more and I'm sure these are just some of
the topics that we will discuss today V
welcome to the show thank you so much
for joining me thank you for having me
it's a pleasure this is really exciting
uh yeah as I said in the intro we share
a lot of interests uh that might appear
quite Niche to people but actually you
know as far as I can tell pertaining to
their lived experience every every
moment so it's it's worthwhile
dissecting funnily enough the first time
I think I'd heard of you was actually
from jackob Javi um in the conversation
I had with him and he said that you know
Thomas metzinger's work perhaps better
than Thomas and certainly better than
anyone else um so so I I I wonder
whether we could start by outlining some
of these crucial um Concepts that
sometimes seem a bit counterintuitive to
people so for example when I say we both
share a love of self- modeling or
phenomenal self modeling what does that
mean what ises this sort of acronym PSM
the phenomenal self
modeling yeah good so um maybe as a um
disclaimer of course um Thomas knows
more about this than me he's um uh in
invented the term self models and has
developed the self model theory of
subjectivity over many many years and um
actually I I I think I can say that
there's probably no living philosopher
who has read as much relevant literature
about topic as as Thomas because he's
devoted his entire career to this and
works a lot and of of course I would
never um even even if I tried be in a
position to know as much about this as
as he does and I I think it might be a
good idea even to invite him to this
podcast he's been invited he has said
yes that was a while ago I've tried to
push it so Thomas if you're listening
which I think he might be you know you
never know um please do come on because
I do yeah so actually it's quite likely
that some of the things that I've be
saying might not be 100% true so Thomas
if you're listening now you may want to
correct some of the misrepresentations
of your work um but anyway yeah what
what is the self model so for me it's I
think easiest to First think about
bodily self models so um just imagine
some creature or a robot that has a body
and has to control the body and as we
all know in many cases control can be
facilitated ated or improved if you have
a model of the thing that you're
controlling and if you want to control
your body and the interaction with the
environment it can be highly useful to
have a model of your body and the model
of your
environment and this is actually then
already a form of self model which is
part of the world model so the world
model would be just be representation of
the world or the relevant part of the
the world the the parts that are
relevant to you and the your
environment and your body is part of
this world
so it's the the self model is part of
the world model but of course that's
just a form of self model and it's quite
primitive probably compared to the self
models that we human beings have and one
thing that distinguishes our self models
is that we don't have only unconscious
self self models but actually we have uh
we also consciously experience the
contents of our self models so this
brings us on to to the notion of a
phenomenal self model where phenomenal
refers to phenomenal experience
phenomenal Consciousness so if you have
not just a um an unconscious self model
but a phenomenal self model you actually
experience your body as your own body
and another form of selfhood that you
then might experience is experiencing
your own
actions as your action so um this is
often called a sense of
agency um that you have over your action
and a sense of ownership that you have
over your body and both can
also um be
uh both can go get lost or be affected
in in various ways and so the these are
some Concepts that are relevant here
there's one thing that I wanted to add
or maybe an example that um Thomas also
likes to use I think is this robot
starfish that
um was developed by Josh bongard and
colleagues and in order to make it
flexible and able it to adapt to changes
to the environment and also to its own
body so for instance one of its lymphs
is um damaged or um is is cut off um you
you want the robot to still be able to
control its body and control movements
and so it can be useful to have a model
of the body self model but of course in
that robot it's just a it's not a
phenomenal self model it's not a
conscious robot so that would be an
example of an
unconscious bodily self
model yeah I
let's start with the body I think that's
a good place to start because as you say
it's kind of the low hanging through the
lower the lowest level of what people
think about in terms of the phenomenal
self model and I think a potential point
of confusion for people is the fact that
the body has what I guess Marlo Ponte
call the jewel aspect which is both that
it can be it's a lived body but it is
also a body that can be observed and can
be objectified and so I guess um the
question here is why do we is there a
difference between saying I am my body I
live through my body or at or or versus
I have a body and what are those
different aspects of selfhood because on
one part I feel like you're getting what
we what we call perspectival I am my
body I live through my body I live yeah
I mean literally through it as a vehicle
through which I can be in the world
versus possession I am some in this case
it seems like people would feel like a
disembodied ego who has a body that they
own is there a way of coalescing these
kind of two canonical features of
selfhood one being possession and one
being perspectival or association with
the lived
body yeah that's a great question so I I
think uh these different perspectives
are to some extent compatible was it
depends on on what you mean so one could
for instance wonder whether a um animal
non human animal which maybe does not
have um a form of Consciousness that is
comparable to to human conscious
experience and that doesn't um reflect
about its own body nevertheless lives
through its
body and so there there there's a live
body but that doesn't mean that we don't
have that we I would say it's just that
we can
also um have different forms of
experience or richer forms of bodily
experience and uh reflect about our own
experience in different
ways
and so having a body versus living
through a body so it it seems to me that
the Liv body is that that's
charact more characteristic of
experiences or situations in which we're
not so much aware of having a body at
all so maybe when we're engaging in some
physical activity um playing sports and
just not not thinking about where our
limbs are but
just moving and
interacting and in the sense living
through the body I I don't know of that
captures what what is usually meant by
that expression yes I wonder whether I
mean it's a good question um we wrote
this paper not you and I me Carl L and
others wrote this paper on Flow States
uh and flow states are exactly this
you're playing sports and we tried to
ground it in a self-modeling
architecture and actually the revisions
have been really useful for that because
I've been able to get a little bit more
concrete on what I'm talking about and
the kind of dichotomy that we're saying
is present there I think I can say this
because hopefully it'll be published
well the prints out is um the
distinction really between a minimal
phenomenal self which is like these
really basil fundamental aspects of
selfhood mindness presentness
perspectival versus epistemic agency or
strong epistemic agency and by that I
mean you know when we let's say plan or
when I'm talking to you and I have to
think about my next sentence there's a
very strong sense of self-guiding that
process where I can use let's say former
resources former knowledge to apply to
to uh deep temporal planning and we're
saying that that's attenuated in flow
and what we're also saying therefore is
that metacognition because I think it's
really important here to distinguish
between pre-reflective self-awareness
and reflective self-awareness and I'm
treating reflective self-awareness as a
metacognitive act your self is
reflecting on itself because um
reflective self-consciousness is itself
a kind of a form of epistemic foraging
that too is attenuated in flow States
but I think the interesting question
there is if I was in flow would I purely
live through my body or could I be
perceptually aware of having a body
nonetheless could I have both um and
these are very difficult questions to
tease out because you know they're
already done retrospectively and so you
only get qualitative reports that's an
interesting Dimension I had thought
about I think okay so I I emailed you
however you know a month ago two months
ago and I said so I've been trying to
get my I've been trying to think about
how metzinger's phenomenal self model
can be coales with active inference and
this is the active inference inight
podcast so I message you I said active
inference takes cognition to be
fundamentally
inferential are the processes within or
or the processes that generate the
phenomenal self model inferential are
the processes that are themselves being
modeled by the phenomenal self
inferential or both because I think van
you you would do a great service
everyone if you could explain that what
Thomas is talking about is kind of the
cognitive system recapitulating its own
data structures into phenomenal space
and I think that's an interesting idea
he talks about this in sort of his 2003
book and 2008 book and some other works
that the phenomenal self model is a in
in an implicitly reflective way is a as
you say a model of itself whether that
is a you know a giving relevant uh
features into Consciousness or Co grain
features into Consciousness whatever it
is but it's a reflective process where
the data structures in the body and
brain are being um transposed into
phenomenal space so maybe we can start
there I may have butchered it and I'm
sure Thomas is pulling his hair out um
but maybe we can start there and and
then feed in inference and see where it
might exist in within those
Cycles yeah so I I think there's
actually quite complex topic
because when we're talking about
self models it it it it seems to
presuppose that there's already an
experienced eye right that I'm I'm I
have a body I am moving my hand and so
on but I don't think that's necessarily
already present in in any in in the most
basic forms of phenomenal self
models and what it's at least the way I
I think about it is that having a at
least a bodily self model is mainly
about just making a distinction
between one between inner and outer as
it were so I'm just trying to avoid the
word um self and and nonself so a
distinction between two types of
processes one is the environment and the
other
is here where I am and
and I I think that actually suffices for
having a a bodily self model or even a
phenomenal self model but of course when
we think about or our experience and the
way we the different forms of self that
we experience there's there's more to it
there there's something like an an eye
and maybe at this point it's useful to
um bring another aspect of the the self
model theory on the table which is the
phenomenal model of the intentionality
relation so quite
PM
exactly and so the idea is that there's
in in
a complex self model phenomenal self
model in which there's not just a
distinction between this belongs to me
this does not belong to me this is my
body this is not my body and so on well
this is
my my action or this is an uncon um
involuntary movement and so on in more
complex self
models you also have this this
perspectival which um and and
subjectivity um in the sense that that
you not just make the distinction
between what is self and nonself or what
is outside and what is inside but also
how you are related to the environment
how you are related to your your body
and how your your thoughts are related
to the world and so on so this brings a
reflexive component to it and makes it
more more complex um I find it a bit
difficult to put this into words so
Thomas could it is difficult I mean so I
can I can hopefully assist I have some
sort of quotes here um great so this is
the way that I've understood it at least
and so we'll start with the quote so
Thomas metzinger 2008 so the pap the ego
tunnel I think is 2009 so this is a
really actually very useful paper um he
wrote in 2008 something like empirical
approach to phenomenal self modeling
it's really it's actually very lucid he
says that
the subjectively experienced content of
the phenomenal self is the
representational content of a currently
active Dynamic data structure in the
system central nervous system and that
it's it's a representational entity
whose content is determined by the
system's very own properties so what I
mean by that is it's it's standing in
for something that is lower level to it
namely these data structures right and
we obviously here are taking as
axiomatic that there are
representational structures and maybe
that's problematic and we can get there
um and then the way that I've always
read the PM is that the cognitive system
can pay attention to the fact that it
itself is directed at other
things and therefore what happens is
that it well I'm not going to say it
makes the inference but it projects into
phenomenal space this notion of itself
and something else I guess my question
here is that's taking as a
presupposition that there is some
division that the self model can model
it can reflect on the fact that its own
attent its own attention can be directed
at so-called external worldly objects or
things in the world
model my question here would be how does
the
brain know what in the sense is external
to it and what is internal to it in the
sense that I can introspectively pay
attention to parts of my own lived
experience but not but have a sense of
mindness
and not feel that kind of Duality or
that distinction but if I pay if in
princip I pay attention to the chair
next to me that feels you know like a
separate object to me so if the brain is
recapitulating some distinctions that
are in its self model I guess my real
question is are we not as you say
already invoking an a priori distinction
between the thing that's paying
attention and the attended
object yeah so if I understand
understand your question correctly um
then the answer would be yes and so what
you you um mentioned knowledge so how
does the brain know and of course
knowledge requires truth so you're
assuming that there is effect um to um
to the matter whether something is
really inside or outside or something is
really I or or mine or self or not self
and um I don't think we have to make
this assumption that there is that these
are truth claims and that the brain has
knowledge about this but it does have to
make some prior assumptions about that
and these can
be can be um
delusions so
um in in that sense I I think the
question how how does a brain know can
be dissolved but of of course then the
question is where where do these priers
come from and
[Music]
um why why are they relatively immune to
revision and what happens if they do
breakdown or the the sense of self
dissolves and so on so might it be
feasible to say that you know at the
very bottom level all we have is
attention in some way um recognize that
I almost well I did commit this kind of
dualistic fallacy when I said there is
the attender and the attended object
seems to me that actually that that
might be a an inference too far rather
there just is the attention onto these
kinds of objects in these data
structures again metzinger puts his far
be than I do he says that when he talks
about the pmir the phenomenal model of
the intentionality relation he says that
you mentally simulate yourself as
currently being directed at a Target
object or goal State um and that's a
really interesting notion right this
mental simulation of
yourself maybe he's committing a
linguistic uh you know fallacy there
that there's a self there in the first
place um
so so we can pay attention let's say to
the fact that we can be targeted at
certain areas of our um Phenom of our
data State space but then we can also
pay attention to the fact that we're
paying attention
and that seems to me I don't what you
think about this proposal that seems to
me to be maybe the heart of reflective
self-consciousness that I can pay
attention to the fact that there seems
to be something that is paying attention
to that which I'm that which is that
where which is where attention is going
to there's a kind of triple
hierarchy um one does that sound like a
feasible uh you know underlying
explanation of metacognitive
self-concept ization or reflective
self-consciousness and
two how deep do those recursive patterns
go what I mean by that is like how many
times can I reflect on my own
attentional processes and I know lar s
Smith and others have been doing this in
terms of So-Cal meta awareness but I'm
thinking more in terms of actually the
underlying phenomenal reality of being a
self is there a point in which the very
notion just
becomes uh you know irreconcilable with
a certain degree of recursive operations
yeah um great question so um regarding
this this triple distinction I um I
think that's already quite difficult to
imagine so maybe we can uh just try
to um clarify this and and just re
restate this again sure um together but
before that there's something that um
came to my mind because uh when we think
about how how does a brain know um what
what's inside um and what's in outside
and but when it comes to I mean there
there's some to to some extent there
there might be truth to to these um to
to claims about this and
um so when it comes to attention we can
just make a this really broad
distinction between um attention
attentional processes that are driven by
external
influences so when some Salient object
or process process loud noise and the
environment suddenly captures my
intention and we can contrast that with
cases in which I'm uh controlling my my
attention and so the changes in
attention are generated or caus caused
by more caused by internal processes
than by external processes and the the
brain can make inferences about that and
can be more or less accurate about
whether some changes in attention have
been more caused by external or internal
processes and it can make sense to model
attention to improve these inferences
and improve the control of attention and
so on maybe we can use this to just re
redescribe this triple distinction that
you mentioned because because I'm not
sure I I fully got what you okay yeah I
I I'm aware that there are lots of
layers to this um as is the problem when
we talk about hierarchies so I can
actually read I was thinking maybe it's
best for me to just read what I've so
this is this is so if people go and look
at that flow paper right now on the
pre-print server they won't see this
hopefully I'm not spoiling anyone's
party uh By the time this comes out hope
this is at the very end of a review
process so hopefully it's fine um anyway
people can shout at me if they want but
I wrote so it's my words um I said in
planning so we're talking about
epistemic agency in planning the
organism not only knows that it is
intentionally directed at something else
yielding a weak form of epistemic agency
and perspectival but it is also in the
act of knowing about its own knowledge
which encodes as M multiple
counterfactual representations of what
might unfold as a result of my actions
in the section of my current Eco Niche
that I seem to control in this way
planning involves strong epistemic
agency since the cognizer can
epistemically model itself as
epistemically agentive I.E it can come
to know its own capacity to control
itself and its econiche over protracted
period of time through stored knowledge
and then I go on to say that that
self-modeling process is transparent in
the sense that the agent often does not
know that it knows its intentional
objects rather there just is the sense
of epistemic agency which permeates a
pre-reflexive of self awareness this is
where the triple thing comes in when the
agent does enter a state of knowing the
fact that it knows its epistemic
capacities it evolves into a
phenomenologically metacognitive
metamodeling or perhaps meta epistemic
organism which reflects on its
being
yeah so that I I think the the issue
that I had when writing this was you
have to start from the original if
you're using the metzinger foundation
you have to start with the original
basis which is that the self model
itself is a simulation it's a
recapitulation of a data structure but
it's a recapitulation data structure
which can itself be uh reflected on and
that reflected that can also be
reflected on so that's where I'm
building in this nature of hierarchical
recursion how does that sound to your
ears and again what what what does it
mean for us to continue to go up these
recursive ranks like what happens for
example if I like is there a point where
I just really concretize my sense of
self or is it does it actually almost
become dispersive because all I realize
that's going on is that I'm paying
attention and I'm just paying attention
at different levels of the hierarchy so
I'm kind of curious about what you think
might be the phenomenological
consequences of going up this hierarchy
of reflective
recursion yeah so I don't think I can
give a full answer to this question
because there might be multiple things
going on so when I'm not just planning
my my actions or planning how
to how to interact with the environment
or whatever but also reflecting upon my
planning becoming aware that I'm
planning I might be evaluating this I'm
becoming aware of the fact that
I'm uncertain about different options or
I might become aware of the fact that I
really want to do one
thing
and so this might then lead to further
experience experience of of of certainty
or maybe also um or or not uncertainty
right or confidence that I'm making a
good decision
or
doubtfulness about the decision and I
think we can then repeat this process
and reflect upon this already
metacognitive
process but the
resulting experience that we have might
not add too much so I don't know if if
it makes sense to say I'm I'm confident
about the confidence that I have in mind
my confidence and my
confidence and so yes I mean it sounds
you know on one hand one could read that
as a genuinely vertical recursion on one
hand you can also read it as a kind of
like the way people talk about the fact
that a triple Bluff is the same as a
single Bluff you know we might actually
just turn our you know turn our heads
onto our Tails so to speak and and end
up actually experiencing same it's a
it's a curious inquiry um someone needs
to model that maybe I need to model that
um just um um what what I wanted to say
is that I I think it makes a lot of
sense for three levels or or um three
recursions and
then above and beyond that I I really
don't have a clear intuition and it's
probably an empirical question also to
what extent it can improve
control and um as I said just from the
point point of view of experience we we
we can mentally build further models
further iterations but they might not
have a real functional significance for
the for the um lower order
processes good okay we will park the
self models I had to do it because it's
been a bug bear of mind but we'll get
Thomas on and we'll we can all chat out
together and see where we end up um
there's a broader question here about
the so-call generative
passage um which is this idea that uh is
really nicely articulated in Maxwell
Ramsey's 2022 Pap with and and
colleagues of course um which is this
idea that okay we kind of have two
things that we are trying to balance one
is experiential reality lived experience
and the other are the in some sense the
tools of science that's one thing the
other thing could also be let's say
neurological
systems and um RAM and colleagues
present free forms of what they call De
generative passage or there's kind of
ways of tying those things together one
is ontological and so that's not
necessarily a subscription to
reductionism it's not necessarily saying
that phenomenal reality is
neural structures but that's one option
whether it's super that's that whole
conversation one is epistemological
which is that the kind of tools that we
use in our science um can be applied
fruitfully or can be used to describe
and explain phenomenal reality lived
experience and the last one is
methodological naturalization which I I
think I've been using a little bit more
in my own writing which doesn't really
have a commitment it's quite agnostic
about ontological epistemological claims
and just says well we can do some good
explanatory work by thinking about PP
schema or predicted processing or
whatever it is um but I'm not going to
say anything about whether Consciousness
is these uh these you know architectures
or neurons I was curious about I think I
think Thomas I I don't want to speak on
his behalf and you'll be able to say
better than I do I feel like he's quite
materialist or reductive about this um
and at least this is something that came
to my attention from Julian Kine when I
spoke to Julian on this podcast um who
was very keen to reject that
reductionism and
Forefront uh intentional experience and
Forefront lived experience and say that
that's irreducible so I was just curious
about where you stand on on this
generative passage and I guess the the
sourest question is the ontological
passage yeah um deep question
so so first of all I I think different
views on this all make sense and are
useful and there there's a lot of
uncertainty about how different levels
of reality relate to each other
and so to some extent we just have
to follow some some assumptions that
we make and and then there will be
different views that are compatible with
the models and
data that we have so I'm not claiming
that we can say well we we can obviously
we can
reduce um conscious experience to
brain activity or something like that
and it's to some extent also an open
question for me what role computational
models actually play
in explaining conscious
experience and what well do they
play yeah so I I think there's when it
so the maybe the simple answer or once
simple answers to say well Consciousness
is so
puzzling it's so difficult to grasp its
different features and talk
about what we are experiencing from
moment to moment it's difficult to put
that into
words and computational models can help
to make certain ideas a bit more
precise
and this might then just
be very on on a
very in in a very simple
way um a use of computational models not
that it's it's not even an explanation
it's just trying
to provide a better Des description of
that which we want to
explain what are the properties the
different features of conscious
experience that we need to explain and
computational models I think
can very legitimately be used
to provide such more detailed
descriptions and once you have that you
can of course then try to make
predictions
about the
implementation in the brain or make
predictions about how conscious
experience will change in certain
situations or you can compare
to
to um descriptions of conscious
experiences that we have to
phenomenological reports from persons in
Altered States of conscious
experience and so on and then at some
point you you may Wonder well maybe
these comp computation models provide
more than just a metaphor for this that
is useful to describe complex and
puzzling features of
experience maybe they also point to the
mechanisms and go some way towards
explaining how conscious experience
arises or why it has the features that
it has even if we cannot maybe explain
why there is conscious experience in the
first
place and
to the extent that the computation
models that are used are also
neurobiologically at least not
implausible and we might be able to find
some empirical confirmation or to the
extent that empirical neural biological
and
um data from cognitive cognitive
Neuroscience are compatible with these
models we might be inclined to make
stronger claims about the relationship
between conscious experience and
computational models and
neurobiological
processes and of of course I'm so
my I ideally we'd have very detailed
computational models that can be used to
describe predict and maybe even control
many features of conscious
experience and ideally we know how they
might be implemented in the brain and
therefore have
some really have something like a
computational um explanation of certain
features of
experience but I can also understand
if some some people might be more
hesitant in saying that though now that
I'm thinking about it um I'm Tous
actually I have to I guess I have to uh
watch the episode with julan KY because
the long one yeah
okay yeah I'd be really interested in
what what exactly his his view on these
matters is yeah we go pretty deep
actually
um yes yeah he he was very much striking
down the line of the irreducibility of
conscious experience which I don't think
is necessarily that controversial um but
he was very
you know he was he was being stubborn
about that point I don't think he'd be
upset if I said that um yes yes okay
good um we can remain agnostic the hard
problem is the the hard problem and
unfortunately it's the most frequent
question that I ask uh and no one has
solved it for me yet and I don't think
they will so I'm G to ask a kind of what
Charmers might say is a less hard
problem or an easier problem um which is
about the features of Consciousness
especially as it's lived by us um is all
Consciousness self
consciousness um I would say no it's not
so I'm I'm I'm not an expert on this
this topic and I haven't read Thomas's
new book
NE but I um I intend to and hope
hopefully then I will know a bit more
about this but I take um reports from
people who have who claim to have
experienced States
of uh nonsubjective
experience seriously or think we we we
should not uh reject these
reports and I'm definitely open to the
possibility and also find the strategy
of trying to look at the simplest form
of conscious experience which may not be
a form of
self-consciousness I find that quite
promising yes so do I um does this map
on to something that I think you've
written about indeed you have um subject
unity and phenomenal Unity is there a
link there what well maybe we can start
with what's the difference between
subject unity and phenomenal
Unity yeah so that that's um
quite can can can become quite
complicated
it and so first of all subject Unity can
mean different things some people just
mean well different experiences that are
had by a subject are subject unified if
they're had by the same subject of
experience now what what is a subject of
experience and some people just identify
a subject with an organism so and in
that
sense subject Unity would
not
entail subjective experience or having a
having some form of
self-consciousness would just mean
subject Unity would then just mean that
there's a conscious organism that has
different experiences at the same time
so and these are all subject unified in
the sense that they are had by the same
subject but of course if you have a
formal self-consciousness
you might say that there's different
form of subject Unity maybe one in which
you're you you have
different
self-conscious experience or different
conscious experiences that are all forms
of self consciousness and somehow refer
to the same same
self something along these
lines yeah so what going back to the
kind of notion that all Consciousness is
self-consciousness goes back to actually
what Mr kin said um so he's got this
paper I think it's a 2018 paper I'll
double check that uh the no 2020 the
free energy in the self an ecological
inactive interpretation he Sayes very
clearly um he says in line with the
arguments of the phenomenologists I will
claim that every feeling must be felt by
someone it must have mindness built into
it if it is to feel a particular way
such a it's such a strong claim
and again I haven't read Thomas's new
book but I do kind of understand this
perspective because at least for example
let's talk about if if one was imagining
depersonalization it's a
depersonalization experience for who
right or if you think about someone
who's experiencing a psychedelic
experience it isn't so much that
perspectival itself is
eliminated it's more that one maybe has
this more Oceanic sense of self which
which is dispersive and that but that
still arguably is a
qualia for the self right or for the the
space of awareness that is inow with
perspectival so I'm just curious about
whether you can think again that this is
a tricky question it's a big question um
and there probably isn't in we can't
probably conceive of this at all but
sort of well I guess actually the
question I'll start with is when I learn
about Consciousness for example I
learned that there were three
fundamental tenants to a consciousness
experience qualia intentionality and
subjectivity this is what the British
schooling system teaches you it when I
hear sort of Julian speak about well
you're always going to have that perspec
iess or intentionality it's always
something for
you can we you know is there a way that
we could say okay some features at least
out of those three that I've just picked
up are more fundamental than others and
that we can have this very very minimal
conscious experience or minimal
phenomenal experience the MP another
acronym um
and what would you say are the defining
characteristics of a minimal phenomenal
experience
therefore yeah I can only say it's an
empirical question so we can speculate
about what the minimal form of
experience might be but it seems that
there's a lot going on in ordinary
waking experiences that can get lost in
Altered States Of Consciousness but what
exactly will remain I I I I don't know
so Thomas can say more about that is
there a problem
with relying on phenomenological reports
to inform such
questions yeah so to to some extent
there's of course the challenge that
these reports are given in retr respect
and oh how do you say retrospect yeah
just yeah yeah
yeah
and then so some people say well it's
it's a bit paradoxical if you say you
have had an experience in which you were
not present or something like
that but um I
I so and and one of of course the the
mere fact that you can remember such
experiences doesn't mean
that
you you you must have had a form of
self-consciousness or that there must
have been subjectivity in the experience
and also when people say well I realize
that I had not been there that there was
no sense of self or no no form of self
consciousness I realized that when
I when I transition transitioned into um
the ordinary form of conscious
experience so while as as it were the
the self was returning I realized hey
there there's
something additional
coming to my conscious experience so it
could not have been there
before yeah that's very interesting
that's really
interesting yeah I guess it makes me
think you know um to even have those
reports whether that's in the internal
speech or external reports requires
propositional language and in my
conceptualization of the scale of
phenomenal self- modeling propositional
language is super high up in the
epistemic agent it's the way that we
plan it's the way that we reflect on our
own being and so on and it sometimes
makes me think well is the lack of is
there a bias there when we don't have
the capacity for propositional claims
either internally or externally we're
biased to think that that constitute
some form of self Annihilation and the
reason why I think that is because like
testimonies for example about flow
States they'll say at least the
testimonies won't be as concrete as this
but the researchers interpretations
which are problematic will say the self
disappeared or there was there was a
reduced
self-awareness that's probably a weaker
form of that claim
well I think the all we're really coming
to here is that you just need to get a
lot more particular about what part of
the self model you're talking about and
how it's being attenuated or accentuated
um and actually I think hopefully for
the listeners what they're kind of
gathering is the self is not this kind
of single monolithic thing that we take
it to be and maybe that's the influence
of day cart and the tradition that
followed from him but rather it's a
complex
hierarchical well appearance in many
ways but also potentially underlying
data structure
that uh will oscillate and modulate and
change given different
contexts good um let's take that a
little bit broader now into just yeah
maybe just one one thing to to make it
slightly more concrete so um what what
is I I think very plausible is to assume
that a sense of temporal self-location
can get lost so you can have conscious
experiences in which there's no time no
temp
experience you don't experience any now
as it were or maybe only now but not as
distinguished from future and past and
then experiences in which you're not
identifying yourself with some place in
space so there's no spatial self
location
and if I understand Thomas correctly he
would suggest that in such minimal
phenomenal experience there certain some
potential for
certain control processes is is still
experienced so what I mean maybe we can
try to illustrate this with attention so
you can either be in the process of
controlling or changing your attention
and have the experience of being in
control have an an experience of
attentional
agency and you but you can also have a
um a sense of control of the potential
for changing your focus of attention so
you you know now you're fixating
focusing your attention on something or
maybe on on my voice but you are aware
of the fact that you could shift your
focus of
attention
and this is so this this potential
aspect
might be something that in in one form
or the other could still be present in a
minimal phenomenal
experience and Thomas can
probably describe this more eloquently
and more detail it also makes me think
what are the prerequisites for
attention it makes me think that
something like temporality or just some
Dynamic needs to be there right because
how are you going to go from one thing
to the other without it being overtime
which also makes me think that it might
have to be also over space because well
I guess we also have covert you know
mental attention not covert attention
mental attention whether that's going
through some space is kind of depends on
how you define space that's a really
interesting question I guess yeah
there's a there's a nice link there you
could say okay I've got a function that
remains in the minimal phenomenal
experience but let me think also about
what the necessary features of the
experience or the world would have to be
for me to have that function um yeah it
makes me think of these um so-called
pure Consciousness events uh which I
came to know about through John BVI and
he sort of describes how in these pure
Consciousness events um so adjectival
qualia redness bless sweetness
disappear but um we Call's adverbial
qualia remain and by that he means
nowness
heess presentness what you know
perspectival and maybe that's a nice
Road in but um yeah I will I probe that
with um with Mr matzinger your well I I
read I've read your papers before and I
read them again because I think they're
so wonderful and interesting you have
these two with call which I love
um and in one of them you talk about
sort of Life mind continuity which I've
also been getting really into because
I've been reading my Evan Thompson um
and in addition to sort of life and mind
distinction you also have a distin
between basic minds and non-basic Minds
which I think is important as a prior
thing to understand before we get into a
sort of Life mind continuity so at just
a very basic level what would you say is
the distinction between a basic mind and
a non Basic
mind um yeah so if I remember
correctly I I think the uh we we mainly
make this distinction in terms of
representation so a basic mind would be
one that does not have representations
and a non-basic mind is one that has
representations good and how does that
feed so how does that feed so um when EV
was talking about mind and life
continuity he was kind of seeking
underlying uh functions structures
processes that are involved both in the
constitution of mind and life so for
example autop poesis
self-organization um or what else would
he have had um operational closure these
are all things that were coming out of
sort of the dynamical systems theory and
Vera's work and now we've got Act of
inference so I was wondering whether how
does Act of inference because I think at
one point you say in that paper um I
won't missp speak I think I've got the
quote here all systems possessing a mark
of blanket have properties that are
relevant for understanding the mind and
Consciousness if such systems have
mental properties then they can have
them partly by virtue of possessing a
Markov blanket and hence your marov and
monism this is I think is this is the F
this is a 2020 paper so not the life
mind one but it is it calls to mind a
sort of Life mind continuity because as
inference postulates anything that
exists has a mark of blankets and it's
doing you know can be seen as if it's um
parametrizing basian beliefs about the
external state so everything has a
markup blank anything that we can call a
thing as a markup blanket and as you say
anything having a markup blanket
properties are relevant and I think
you've been very careful with your words
here for understanding
mind why would that be the case and also
how does that how is that the case
without us resorting to a sort of pan
psychism yeah that's a good question
really fair question because I think
what we say in that paper can easily be
misunderstood and
maybe yeah we should have found a better
way of of conveying what where I I
should have found a better way of
conveying what I had in mind so the idea
is not that as soon as you have a mark
of blanket you have have a mind and and
it just becomes more complex
the idea is more that as soon as you
have the mark of blanket if you are self
organizing
system which conforms to the free energy
principle so there's a mark of
blanket
and you can then then you can interpret
internal
States as
encoding probabilistic beliefs about
external States given blanket States and
this is the feature that is also
relevant to understanding I would
claim the mind it does not mean that
once you have that you already have a
mind in an interesting sense but it's
just that if you have a
mind
then you can describe you can understand
I would
say mental processes in terms of minimiz
ing variation free
energy and then and and understand them
them in terms
of and in terms of computational
processes that involve these
probabilistic beliefs about external
States given blanket States and so the
the what what I really wanted to say is
that this is not something that comes at
at a later stage when we have really
complex system
but according to the FR energy principle
we already have that for very simple
self organizing systems and so to
contrast this with um anactive
approaches that would
say well we have these simple systems
and they are still that they can be
quite autonomous and so on and
remarkable and so remarkable in fact
that even higher even nonbasic Minds in
in a different sense or maybe I
shouldn't say non Basic here but so even
more complex system most complex
organisms like us that have
Minds um they they many of their
properties can be explained many of
their mental properties can be
explained by reference to the same
Dynamics and features that are already
present in simple autonomous
systems and maybe you don't even need to
invoke representations to explain these
more complex
organisms and I'm suggesting well no
because you already have some form of as
if representationality or intentionality
and even simple self organizing
systems and this as if representation
ality can then um or you
can making some some further assumption
you can argue that in more complex
systems it's not just a useful way of
describing them as if they had
representations but they they actually
have
representations and so there there's
something in in simple self organizing
systems that already there uh that's
also there in in more complex organisms
that have a mind and Consciousness and
in order
to understand the
mind to the extent that the fre energy
principle and active inference are
useful to understanding the mind we have
to invol we have to refer to these
internal States and how they encode
beliefs about external States given
blanket States and that's some something
we already have in very simple set of
organizing systems so that's just the
the idea which I think um if described
in the way in which we did can be really
misleading no I hope this also suggests
how it avoids pan
psychism not I'm happy to elaborate them
no I think so um and to be fair you make
it actually pretty clear um you say that
you sort of propose some rhetorical
questions does it follow that all
systems with a mark of blank have a mind
are such systems conscious this
formalism itself does not answer these
questions so I think you I think you're
fine I think uh maybe what people might
be slightly confused over is this notion
of an information geometry if they've
ever read this this paper so the way
that I understood it was you have sort
of two informational geometries let's
say two ways of uh describing a
um a system that has a mark of blanket
internal and external States right that
coupled system and you have the
so-called intrinsic geometry which
actually just describes the behavior of
the internal state if it you know um I
don't would that well I'll I'll ask
whether that includes the particular
States I the blanket States and then you
have the so-called extrinsic geometry
which are the beliefs that the internal
States actually encode about the
external States so that's a very sort of
rough um draft that the distinction
between the intrinsic geometry and the
extrinsic geometry would be great if you
could flesh that out a little bit more
but how does that pertain here to um
mind because I think you also make it
quite clear that that property of the
mark of blanketed system itself is
relevant to the question of
mind yes so it it is in a sense relevant
but I would say in a rather trivial way
so yeah I I think this can be really
confusing and I'm not sure how useful it
is
to even refer to information geometry to
get at these more General conceptual
points but so an information
geometry is just you you have a space in
which every Point corresponds to a
probability distribution mhm and then
you can
um you can have different shapes and um
manifolds in in this uh space so for
example surfaces and compute distances
between points distances between
probability
distributions and these distances will
not be ukian distances so it's it's just
um different form of um the different
kind of space yeah and so every so the
internal States if you interpret them
as as U probabilistic beliefs about
external States given blanket States you
can identify them with points in
the in an information geometry and then
the way in which these beliefs are
updated and which updated in which they
change can then be described as a
trajectory through that yeah um space
and you can Al and you also have a
different space of probability
distributions for the what one could
call the physical dynamics of the system
so if you're
not referring to probability
distributions encoded by internal
States but about the probabilities of
internal States or maybe an
paths then you you can also identify
them with points in in such a
space space of probability
distributions but
it's a different these are different
probability
distributions and the thing just is that
you you can then describe trajectories
through both of these information
geometries and in in a way they are two
sides of two different sides of the same
coin so the idea is that you can
describe the physical dynamics of these
self-organizing
systems equivalently by describing them
in terms of the Dynamics the belief
Dynamics or basian
mechanics in terms of changes of
probability distributions encoded by
internal States rather than in terms of
probability
distributions
Over States of the system yeah yeah okay
so I think the reason why this might be
a bit confusing for people is because
then people have heard that all that
we're talking about when we talk about
internal States is this parametrized if
that's a word beliefs about external
States that's all the internal states
are right they just are distributions
over external States okay so that that
that might be a commitment anical
commitment to say that but let's take
that as a kind of starting point that's
what we mean by internal States and then
we have an intrinsic geometry which is
mapping the evolution of those
beliefs right um and that's over
time but that given that those beliefs
just are over the external States is
there not an isomorphism between the
intrinsic and the extrinsic in so far as
when the intrinsic changes I.E when the
path of the state of the internal States
changes by necessity the extrinsic
information geometry would have changed
because the intrinsic the internal
States just are the probabilistic
distributions that the extrinsic
geometry
defines so for me I can't right now see
how there's a I say they're
isomorphic I almost think well I almost
can't see how they're not one and the
same but I might be missing something I
probably am missing I'm always missing
something no I I think you're on the
right track
so there yeah essentially just just two
different ways of describing the system
but okay so but do they so what is the
utility of that I guess is the question
because to me it seems like
you you just a very philosoph you know
philosophy of science point the utility
of two different descriptions of the
same
phenomenon it has to have some utility
right like if we're talking about heat I
talk about how it feels to be hot or I
can talk about the velocity of particles
within a heat bar or within whatever but
that's useful because one I can attend
to phenomenological facts and the other
one I can attend to facts about
physics whereas this it just seems
like primy there are two dis inct
descriptions but under the blanket
because the internal States really just
are probability distributions about
external States there's nothing over and
above their evolution beyond that which
can be described by the intrinsic
information geometry so is there
something more to these two types of
descriptions which make them distinct or
is it is it
just some semantics I I don't want to
say that because that always sounds very
derogatory and I don't mean to be
derogatory yeah so um on on on the one
hand what one could say yeah and to some
extent it's just semantics but that
doesn't mean that it's not useful to use
one instead of the other description so
think about describing a system in terms
of
representations so you you can of course
just
describe the vehicles without referring
to the content and so you're
dispensing with the representational
description and just focusing on the
physical material
realizers of the representations and
that that's fine but um you typically
get some benefit
of going to a different level of of
description so when you're describing a
system in terms
of um representations you have you can
refer to
contents provideed normative description
so the they the system can have true or
false representations or they can be
more or less accurate yeah
and so and and you also have that
for uh the the Basin mechanics so it's
in a way it's just a different way of
describing the system and you don't need
that you can describe the system you
can stick to your physical purely
physical
description um and don't need to refer
to probabilistic beliefs but this gives
you some benefit so on on the one hand
it reduces
complexity
because when you're referring to
internal States as
encoding probabilistic beliefs you're
actually C graining the
system and uh not just talking
about
the say the the um billions of of
neurons but about neural populations
that encode different beliefs and so you
can um reduce the complexity of your
description but
still um given that if the free energy
principle is correct you um have an an
equivalent
description it's it can still be as
accurate or almost as accurate but
without having to deal with all the
unnecessary
details so that's one benefit that you
get just a reduction of
complexity yes I sense that that's a
reduction of complexity for the
scientist I guess really you very much
put it nicely in terms of the
distinction between the vehicle and the
content which certainly pertains when
we're talking about representational
systems I guess my point really here is
that I arguably think that there is no
vehicle the internal state is not a
vehicle of anything and I think this
really comes down to actually how you
describe it because the way you describe
it is that they encode probabilistic
belief whereas I think if you're
abandoning the vehicle you can just say
they are
prob um and if I think if you have the
vehicle but so sorry so then it seems
like you're dispensing with the physical
purely physical
description and just happy to to say
well we we only need the basil mechanics
right I I would just say that um what we
we are sometimes misled to think that
active inference entails a uh
representational approach
and yeah you so you can do the
descriptions in terms of the basian
mechanics that itself will map on to
some physical
organization
um but I don't think it necessarily
dispenses with it it just says that when
we as scientists try to carve up these
spaces we are
making well when we are making these
very strong distinctions and this is
something that I've been tackling with
literally ever since I disc CED active
inference and learned about the free
energy principle which
is what is unique about the internal
States right what what what is there
something over and above the
parametrization of beliefs about
external states there in the internal
states that make the thing the thing it
is
I.E are is all that we are preferred
external
States or are we a thing that is trying
to get to preferred external States if
you can see the difference there so that
I think that again comes back whether we
embody a generative model or have a
generative model and I think I've been
leaning in terms of the just in terms of
the physics towards the idea that we
embody a generative model all that means
is that we are just a bundle of external
States and you can describe the the the
direction the information travel of
those external States in terms of Asian
inference but the internal external
distinction is somewhat illusory
because we just are the external States
might sound very s Buddhist actually but
um yeah I think maybe that's where we we
don't necessarily we're not disagreeing
but maybe where I don't really see the
strength of this this distinction
because I don't really see the strength
of the distinction between the internal
and the external and arguably I just see
it as a instrumental tool I don't know
if that answers your
question um yeah no no
um that's a good point also uh speaks to
what we talked about in the beginning
right to what
extent there's a fact to the matter
whether something is internal or
external yeah I just think a big mistake
that people well I think a big stumbling
block that people have although it may
also paradoxically be a very useful tool
for them is to think of active inference
and this is more like a meta
conversation about how we get educated
on these things think of active
inference as a theory that needs a
homunculus and I'd argue that it's not
but then you have to be very concrete on
the fact that free energy principle and
active inference is a Theory of
physics um and it's just
describing physical manifolds well not
even physical manifolds in this
statistical manifolds whether they're
physical mental so on and that I think
gets you away from the kind of more
hunzed predictive coding predictive
processing approach um and so again I
mean ultimately I think it comes down to
one's aims and I think as far as I'm
whereare the math stands up on both
fronts um and maybe it's a question I
need to speak to KL about which is you
know so the free engine principle rests
upon the mark of blanket
distinction why do we not just have one
unified State space where things are
tending well different things are
tending towards different manifolds why
do we need them to be tending towards
those
manifolds over the parametrization of
external States and I think here the
really important point is and we' come
back to over and over again on this
podcast the free energy principle tells
you what things look like they're doing
not necessarily what they are doing um
and maybe that deflates to use Carl's
favorite word it deflates some of our
worries about really making any strong
ontological claim right it's just a
descriptive thing then that makes me
think well what's the uh what's the
point but I don't think what's the point
so I think it's important and I think
you do get some you do get some good
stuff out of it so yeah that there's
just one thing I I would like to add so
um that I I think there's one
perspective from from which we one
can argue that it's not completely
arbitrary whether we say we we interpret
or
we describe internal States as
probabilistic beliefs and identify them
with with these beliefs and just focus
on this or whether
we also think about the the other
perspective other way of describing the
Dynamics of um the system because the
the same basian mechanics the same
dynamics of belief can be realized in
different ways and so you you can
simulate this on a computer or you can
implement it in a living
organism and I think when
we consider the possibility of
artificial Consciousness this actually
may make a
difference because if we're just
focusing on
the if we're just seeing internal States
as probabilistic beliefs and nothing
else then we cannot make this
distinction between different types
different kinds of
realizations
of variation of free energy
minimization and I think it's a an open
question and very important question to
what
extent there can be a conscious
experience in a computer in a digital
computer with a classical
architecture or
to what extent it needs a biological
body or maybe a robot that can interact
with the
environment
and for for this reason I I think it's
important to keep this to yeah not not
to um ignore this distinction between
two ways of looking at the system yeah
fair enough guess uh ultimately as well
I do think is important to say is that
it depends on how you define
beliefs um and that's something that we
all like not me and you necessarily but
all of us equivocate on the whole time
because we're not clear where we're
talking about folk psychology beliefs or
basian beliefs and I guess when I'm
talking about the internal States just
being manifestations of external States
I'm talking about basian beliefs in
terms of the the beliefs that those
internal states have when I'm talking
about the rejection of the homuncular
view of the internal States in many ways
I'm re rejecting I'm not I'm not
rejecting the basian beliefs that they
have or embody or entail or so what I'm
rejecting the folk psychology hunzed
representational propositional beliefs
that we talk about in philosophy so I
think that's an important thing as well
for people to bear in mind that there's
often risk in Act of inference that we
equivocate and talk past one another
again not you and I generally but you
know everyone because we don't get
concrete on what we're talking about
with respect to beliefs but that's a
nice interesting um segwave because you
wrote this paper in 2022 with Carl on AI
eics in computational Psychiatry and it
actually takes us nicely full circles to
Mr metzinger Professor metzinger me um
because he actually was the first person
I ever read in the ego tunnel talking
quite explicitly about the effects of
generating artificial intelligence like
re and in a very philosophically robust
way obviously people have been talking
about well what are the ethics in terms
of job opportunities in terms of um you
know trolley problems when my car might
run over a grandmother or a child and so
on but I think what Thomas said that was
really impactful for me was we might be
actually creating conscious life so it's
not just the you know it's not just the
the ethical effects on us it's actually
the generation of sentience feeling
Consciousness into the universe and
uptick in that whereby those things
start to actually have moral value which
are arguably equivalent or perhaps given
their greater complexity and depending
on how you define your morality more
important than us so you can throw out
the window your kind of classic Sam
Harris worry that AI is just going to
stomp on us like we're ants right that's
one ethical issue about us but also and
again this is I don't mean that this
should happen or will happen but
arguably you know those AI creatures are
going to have sentience and feelings and
Consciousness just like us and we have
to take their so you know rights or
values if they have them if we give them
that into account so it's not just a
single sided relationship that's going
to emerge I'm curious about what you
think about that is it is it a concern
that we really have to take seriously
that if for example we end up making AGI
and very importantly that AGI is
conscious because I think there's a
really important point there there's a
difference here between intelligence and
Consciousness um what concerns do we
have to have not only about ourselves
but also about what we are bringing into
the world
yeah good I think there are many
different and to some extent related
questions that are relevant here and one
question is of course what what about
the risk of actually creating artificial
Consciousness what consequences would
that have
and should we do it or should should we
refrain from even attempting to create
artificial
Consciousness um there's things become
more
complicated when we also consider the
fact
that there will likely be a lot of
uncertainty about
whether um a given artificial system is
conscious or not so um Eric schwitz
Gable has done a lot of very relevant
and interesting work on this and he
describes the problem roughly as follows
I'll try to
summarize the main ideas but there's um
people who are interested in this can
easily find his Publications and uh
podcast interviews with with ER Eric
schitz Gable um so highly
recommend uh looking these things up and
um so the the basic problem is this um
there might be situations in which there
are artificial IAL systems that may seem
to be conscious and we might in addition
also have no way of being certain that
they are not conscious so there might be
no
um clear evidence as to whether they're
conscious or not even from a scientific
point of view um given that we don't
have a consensus in Consciousness SS we
don't really know what Consciousness is
there's no um generally agreed upon
Theory Of Consciousness and so on and
many different metaphysical views about
Consciousness that all have some
currency so there's a lot of un
uncertainty about which systems could be
conscious and as artificial systems
become more and
more capable and have become have have
more and more impressive cogn ative
capacities there will
likely be points at which
they well seem conscious and also
fulfill some indicators of Consciousness
that we might
have but they might still be quite
different from human beings conscious
human beings or other conscious animals
in in many respects so that there there
will be a lot of uncertainty and there
there two types of errors that one could
make one is believing that such systems
are conscious and maybe also believing
that they therefore deserve moral status
maybe because they can feel pain and
pleasure um so assigning a moral status
to such systems believing that they're
conscious although in fact there's
nothing going on they're completely
unconscious and then there might be
situations in which we have to make
tradeoffs between the interests of human
beings conscious human beings and the
seemingly conscious artificial systems
which are in fact
unconscious so
just if we just think about uh um I mean
just just uh a slightly silly example
trolley case in which we we um can save
five artificial systems that we believe
are conscious or one conscious human
being and of course if these systems
actually are unconscious but we just
think well we
should U be well better safe than sorry
uh we we should not um we we should just
we on the side of being a bit too
liberal and we might uh say would be a
good idea to save the the artificial
systems or in in other situations in
general just um put more weight on their
interests and in
fact um they're they're completely
unconscious
and yeah so that that would be I think
yeah that's a terrifying idea yeah of
course the other case is that there are
artificial systems that don't seem to be
conscious and we firmly believe
or we we um maybe there's also some
uncertainty but um for whatever reason
we decide no um these the systems are
probably not conscious maybe because
they don't seem to be conscious but
actually they are conscious and then in
certain situations we
might without thinking much about it
sacrifice them or um destroy them or
whatever or and and in fact um maybe um
induce a lot um um a lot of suffering in
these artificial systems but without
knowing that so these are two scenarios
that
we I I think would like to
avoid and schwitz Gable certainly argues
for this that we should avoid such
situations namely by avoiding to create
systems for which
there's no certainty about whether
they're conscious or not and so this is
not not
um it's a bit different from metzinger's
position and um the the question of
course is is this really feasible or is
it realistic that we will in the
future um only create systems that are
either clearly non-conscious or that are
clearly
conscious and I think in in order to get
there it would be really useful um to
have a handle on some necessary
conditions for Consciousness that might
not be fulfilled by certain classes of
artificial systems and if for instance
having a body is required for being
conscious then we could rule out that
Consciousness in a computer
simulation so I'm not not claiming that
I have a good argument for this but um
it's I I think it's would be extremely
desirable to
have a Justified account of necessary
conditions for
Consciousness that are not fulfilled by
many artificial systems and so um that
that's um the
line of research that I'm trying to
pursue of finding good reasons to
believe that there are certain necessary
conditions for consciousness of course
the other approach which
um I I must say from
from um from a certain point of view
seems a lot more compelling is to say
well we don't really know what is
necessary for Consciousness or not we
cannot rule out that certain systems are
conscious if they don't fulfill certain
conditions but uh we
can look at theories of Consciousness we
can look at work on animal Consciousness
and derive indicators for
Consciousness and that's this um uh
preprint from last year by um Patrick
butlin Robert long and a whole bunch of
other authors Eric schitz Gale is also
one of the co-authors and they they do
exactly that they say well um under the
assumption of computation of
functionalism uh we can
derive certain number of indicators from
theories of Consciousness and can think
about how they could be implemented in
artificial systems in AIS we can also
assess to what extent they are already
fulfilled by current AI and but based on
this it's highly unlikely that current
AIS are conscious but if future AIS
fulfill many of these indicators it
becomes more likely that they're
conscious so each time a an artificial
system fulfills one of these indicators
the probability that it's conscious
Rises a little sure and of course that's
um very elegant approach because you
don't have to make any strong
metaphysical commitments you can just
say well we we don't really know what
Consciousness is but we can say what
features make it a bit more likely that
a system is
conscious and as soon as we have systems
that fulfill many of these indicators or
many markers of
Consciousness we might reasonably say
well it's highly likely that a system is
conscious and we
should
um assign moral status to the system but
of course then the question is what what
happens in the meantime when we have
many systems that fulfill some
indicators or many but
not maybe not so many indicators that we
can really be certain that these systems
are
conscious and how can we avoid these
situations yes it's fascinating it's
fascinating and we don't have time for
me to put on my philosophers skeptical
hat and
uh and point out all the problems with
trying to find behavioral indicators to
Consciousness which are so obvious that
I don't really need to say them but
again that's the philosophers point and
this more of a pragmatic point which is
we are probably going to have to make
that decision at some point and so why
is actually kind of interesting we're
saying up a sort of basian process with
which to come up with a posterior that a
given object is conscious or not so it's
kind of fun that we're inverting the
basium process to figure out um but as
you know your model is only as good as
its priors and if those behavioral
priors or behavioral indicators are
wrong then you are really barking down
the wrong tree you might be Bay optimal
but your Bay optimal for dysfunctional
purpose um cool that's really yeah
that's fascinating I mean I'd love to go
further but I'm aware that we are
running a bit low on time so you
mentioned this is kind of your main
focus of research at the moment what
else can people expect from you coming
up next couple of months this year and
also how can people get in touch with
you if they want to ask you questions or
just
chat yeah sure um so I'm I have a blue
sky
account and um I I think my blue sky
handle is va. Visa probably should check
but um
I also have a Twitter account I don't
really understand what it is I like
Twitter
but yeah so so I also have a Twitter
account and then my handle is w a w s e
I think
excellent and um and what can people
look forward to reading or or hearing
from you about um and also maybe plug
the workshop that you're at now because
that's a really cool um thing that you
guys are doing yeah so I'm currently at
um the ik in gunner in Germany um ik is
um the interdisciplinary College it's a
spring school for cognitive
science and it's an entire week with a
lot of fascinating courses MH from AI to
neuros science neurot
technology um we also have some more
philosophical
courses uh some more theoretical some
more practical it's a really great
mixture and there many Fascinating
People over here that you can talk to so
I highly recommend coming to the ik and
Guna and um maybe do you have show notes
or something like that for the podcast
maybe you can provide link to the
website is everything goes in the
description I'll put your blue sky in
the description as well I'll make sure I
do that thank you cool and also maybe
maybe one thing what what people can
expect um so I I signed a contract with
MIT press um for a book on artificial
Consciousness so working on and also um
I think I I should remind myself that I
should be busy working on the
manuscript fantastic well
congratulations is that uh do people
know this already or is this a big
reveal have we done have we done an
exclusive break on active inference
insights or do people is this do people
know about this book
already um I I think most people don't
know about it I've just told a few
persons about it but on the other hand
most people don't know me
so yeah true no one knows us well yeah I
forget that I was just trying to sort of
embody a you know speculate you know
speculative Paparazzi esque person I it
very well van this was super fun um I
feel like there's still a lot to get
into um so maybe when Thomas comes it
would be great to have you on even if
you know partially for a bit so we can
get deeper into these ideas and um thank
you for plating me and listening to my
ramblings about recursive properties and
operations it's no thank you thank you
very much for for having me and then
this was really a pleasure so um I think
it we had a nice flow in the
conversation we did we did all right
thank you everyone for watching as well
take care